- 嗨 我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
- Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
字幕翻译/压制：NeXT-X6，旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/KA69Oh3_obY
原视频发布日期：20200430
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
TLI与LTO的区别是，TLI是动作，
而LTO是轨道，其他则等效。
或者说是通过TLI进入LTO。
NASA刚刚宣布了阿尔忒弥斯计划的月球着陆器 出乎了所有人的意料
NASA just announced the lunar landers for the Artemis program and, to everyone's surprise,
SpaceX的巨大的Starship实际上是月球着陆器之一
SpaceX's massive Starship is actually one of the landers
NASA同时还选择了蓝色起源和Dynetics的计划
that NASA chose alongside Blue Origin and Dynetics proposals.
哇  (笑)
Whoa. (chuckles)
这带来了很多问题
And this is bringing up a lot of questions,
其中一些将在我的下一个视频中回答
some of which we'll answer in my next video,
NASA是否应取消SLS而使用Starship或其他商业火箭来完成阿尔忒弥斯计划
Should NASA Just Cancel SLS and Use Starship and/or Other Commercial Launchers for Artemis?
而在这期视频里将会深入了解为什么NASA不应该只用Starship
where we're going to dive deep into why NASA isn't just using Starship entirely,
为什么他们只把它当作月球着陆器来使用
and why they're only looking to use it as a lunar lander.
但是今天我觉得只需要先解决一下关于这两款火箭的争议
But today I think we need to settle a lot of debates here first about these two rockets,
而现在更需要让它俩进行对比
and now more than ever, it's time we truly pit them head-to-head.
因为这很有可能会被载入史册
Because this very well might go down in the history books
因为这两枚火箭同时存在 是很讽刺的事情
as some serious irony that these two rockets even exist at the same time.
我是指 尽管这两种火箭有着类似的运载能力
I mean, despite these two vehicles having very similar capabilities,
但是比其他对立的火箭还要不同
you couldn't come up with two more opposite vehicles
它们有着截然不同的设计理念
with two drastically different engineering philosophies.
我是指 一种火箭由经验丰富的工程师进行了多年的仔细地研制
I mean, one rocket has been meticulously designed and built for years and years by seasoned rocket engineers,
而另一种火箭由拼凑而来的太空牛仔们在德克萨斯州的野地里面建造
and the other is being built in a field in Texas by a patchwork team of space cowboys,
其中一些人之前是在造水塔
some of whom previously built water towers.
那么今天 让我们看看Starship和SLS的历史的进程
So today, let's take a look at the history and progress of Starship and SLS,
包括猎户座飞船和其他任何阿尔忒弥斯计划所需要的东西
including the Orion capsule and everything else necessary for the Artemis missions,
它们的设计考虑 以及运载能力
their design considerations, and lastly, their capabilities.
做完这些之后 再回答问题
Once we do that, I think we can answer the question,
SLS和Starship怎么可能同时存在呢
how is it possible that two rockets like SLS and Starship even exist at the same time.
它们应该同时存在吗？
Should they exist at the same time?
我是指 其中一种很容易成为有史以来最有野心的火箭 而且实际上正在研制中
I mean one is easily the most ambitious rocket ever conceived and actually being worked on,
另一种则是活在过去
and the other is living in the past,
真的就是重复使用退役的航天飞机上扒拉下来的零件
I mean, literally reusing old parts from retired space shuttles.
最后是怎么发展到了这步田地
How on Earth did we even wind up here,
两个有史以来建造的最强的火箭同时上线
two of the most powerful rockets ever made going online at roughly the same time?
好吧 我们已经有很多事情要讲了 让我们开始吧
Well, we've got a lot to cover, so let's get started.
-  [任务控制]三 二 一
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
起飞
and liftoff!
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
-  [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
- 在我们这个视频展开之前
- Before we get too far into this video,
我只需要快速有趣地提下我穿着的这个很棒的月球任务衬衫
just wanted to give a quick, fun shout-out to this awesome Lunar Mission shirt that I'm wearing.
在这个视频的结尾 我会邀请大家来找这件衬衫的复活节彩蛋
At the end of this video, I'll challenge you to find the Easter egg in this shirt.
待会再详细讨论它吧
We'll talk more about that later at the end.
好吧 你是否曾花费两个多月研究 拍摄 编辑 以及给一个视频做动画
Okay, have you ever spent two months researching, shooting, editing and animating a video
快要做完的时候
only to get it completely done
发现在你正准备发布视频的前一天
and find out the day before you were planning to release it
你视频的每一部分都出了问题
that every single bit of your video needs to be blown up,
而你需要重新剪辑视频
and you need to reassemble the scraps?
哦 是的 没错 我不知道那是什么滋味
Oh, yeah, no, no I have no idea what that's like.
如果你是我的Patreon支持者之一
If you're one of my Patreon supporters,
你可能现在就在笑
you're probably laughing right now at
这个视频和这周初的版本的差异有多大
how different this video is from just what you saw earlier this week,
我当然会把它保留在Patreon那里 供后人查看
which I'll keep up in there, Patreon, for posterity's sake.
所以请原谅我 如果你发现这个视频是分段拍摄的
So please forgive me if you can tell that I've shot this video in pieces,
因为它确实是这样(笑)
because I have. (chuckles)
但是我们需要了解很多好消息
But there's a lot of good info that we need to get to.
因为你们知道我
Because you guys know me,
一旦开始了SLS对比Starship的主题
once I got into the topic of SLS vs Starship,
我可能就有点太得意忘形了 只顾着回答自己的问题了
I maybe got a little too too carried away answering my own questions,
深入地了解这些东西 并纠正了许多实话说我觉得是错误的假设
diving in deep and correcting a lot of assumptions that frankly, I had wrong.
但是我已经把这个主题压缩了一下
But I've boiled this topic all the way down,
这样才能深入地讲清楚这些基本知识
and we're going to cover all the bases in great depth,
因为这个主题总是引起很大争议
because this one is nuts and you guys debate this all the time,
那么我们有很多要解决的问题
so we have a lot to settle.
现在 因为我们要讲的东西太多了
Now, because we've got so much to cover,
就像我的所有那些长视频一样
and just like all my long videos,
这里是供你参考的时间戳
here's the timestamps if you need a reference for later.
05:50 - 什么叫超重型火箭
09:00 - SLS和猎户座的历史
18:05 - Starship的历史
22:30 SLS / 猎户座和Starship的进度和清单
27:30 - Starship和SLS的设计理念
34:55 - Starship对比SLS
41:50 - 总结
但认真地说 不要跳着看这个视频
But seriously, don't skip through this video.
你会震惊于我所了解到的一些东西
You'll be shocked at some of the things that I learned,
至少是关于历史的进程的部分
at least about the history and the progress,
当然 也会得出一部分结论
and of course, some of the conclusions as well.
我在简介里也列出了这些主题的快速链接 以及这个视频的文章版本
And I've got quick links to these topics and an article version of this video in the description too.
everydayastronaut.com/sls-vs-starship
好了 在一开始的时候 我需要澄清一件事
Okay, right off the bat, we've gotta make one thing clear.
NASA和SpaceX不是竞争对手
NASA and SpaceX are not competitors.
如果你喜欢SpaceX 你应该为此感谢NASA
If you love SpaceX, you can thank NASA for that.
NASA是SpaceX最大的客户和它的支持者
NASA is SpaceX's biggest customer and their biggest supporter,
所以要记住这点
so let's keep that in mind.
好像这件事现在已经不是很明显了
As if that wasn't obvious now
NASA简直是为了阿尔忒弥斯计划才投资的Starship
that NASA is literally investing in Starship for the Artemis program
还能看到NASA为了商业载人计划在SpaceX的猎鹰9号火箭上涂装着它的标志
and seeing NASA plastered all over SpaceX's Falcon 9 rocket for the Commercial Crew Program,
NASA和SpaceX的关系始于SpaceX刚开始的时候
the relationship with NASA and SpaceX goes back to pretty much the beginning of SpaceX.
我是指 毕竟
I mean, after all,
如果不是NASA一开始为猎鹰9号和龙飞船投入了接近4亿美元
if it weren't for NASA's initial investment of nearly $400 million for the Falcon 9 and Dragon capsule,
再加上商业补给服务和商业载人合同
then plus the multi-billion dollars for the CRS and commercial crew contracts,
可以肯定地是 SpaceX达不到今天的高度
SpaceX most certainly wouldn't be where they are today.
NASA确实在做着不可思议的工作
NASA does incredible things,
没有私人公司真的想做的重要的研究和科学
vital research and science that no private company would or really ever could do,
他们在幕后做了很多常常被忽视的工作
and they do a lot of behind the scenes things that can often go unnoticed.
我的上一个对比SLS和Starship的视频在两年前
In my last video that compared SLS and Starship two years ago,
b23.tv/3BV1V7411L7mS
还是那个Tim难以理解地穿着俄罗斯高空服在他的卧室(做节目)的时光里
back in the Tim inexplicably wore a high altitude Russian flight suit in his bedroom days,
我真的在钻研为什么拿NASA这个组织直接和SpaceX这个私人公司对比并不公平
I really drilled into why it's not fair to compare NASA the organization directly to SpaceX, the private company.
你也许知道 一般情况下
As you probably know, in general,
我希望合作探索太空 并且支持我的观众反对那种党争
I'm team space and I like to encourage my audience to fight tribalism,
同时不要老觉得只有一个方案是最佳的 其他都特别差
and not just think one thing is the best and therefore everything else sucks.
但是 当这个话题转到NASA建造并运营一个火箭的时候
But when it comes to NASA building and operating a rocket,
那么我们能恰当地比较两个系统的好处和坏处
then we can properly compare the pros and cons of those two systems.
因为我已经知道很多观众
Because I already know there's plenty of you out there that are,
在说橙色的火箭差(SLS) 闪亮的火箭好(Starship) 或者相反的话
Orange rocket bad, Shiny rocket good and vice versa.
那么让我们先和和稀泥
So let's come together, sing kumbaya a little,
庆祝下我们已经有了多个超重型火箭了 没错
and celebrate the fact that we have multiple mega rockets in existence, yes.
好吧 既然已经没有了牵手的余地了
Okay, now that the hand-holding's out of the way,
让我们定义一下超重型火箭
let's define the term super heavy-lift launch vehicle.
你知道为什么没有在对比里包含像蓝色起源即将发布的新格伦火箭
So you know why we're not including rockets like Blue Origin's upcoming New Glenn
或者其他重型火箭
or other heavy-lift launchers in this comparison.
航天业认为一个超重型火箭
The aerospace industry considers a super heavy-lift launcher
应该能将超过50吨载荷送入轨道
as a rocket that can carry more than 50 tons into orbit.
超重型火箭当然可以把更大的东西送入轨道
Super heavy-lift launchers can of course put bigger things into orbit,
但这里面真正的含义是有着把更大的东西送入月球的潜力
but what that really means is having enough capability to potentially send large things to the moon
或者让探测器知道外太阳系而不需要花时间的重力助推
or get probes on direct trajectories to our outer solar system without time-consuming gravity assists,
而这可能让探测器进入外太阳系目的地的速度快3倍
potentially getting to outer solar system destinations almost three times faster.
历史上 只有5个超重型火箭发射过
Historically, there's only been five super heavy-lift launchers to ever fly,
而只有4个是成功的
and only four of those were actually successful.
它们是(近地)运力达到140吨的土星五号
They're the Saturn V, which could lift 140 tons,
苏联的失败的N-1火箭可以运载95吨
the Soviet Union's unsuccessful N-I that could have lifted 95 tons,
然后是苏联飞过两次的能源火箭能够运载100吨
then there's also the Soviet Union's twice-flown Energia rocket which could fly 100 tons.
SpaceX公司的重型猎鹰技术上可以运载约64吨
SpaceX's Falcon Heavy technically can loft about 64 tons
在这种情况下三个助推器(两个助推器/一个芯一级)无法回收
if SpaceX chose to expend all three boosters.
虽然这从来没发生过也可能永远不会发生
Although this has never happened and may never happen,
它确实让重型猎鹰变成了超重型运载火箭
it does make Falcon Heavy technically a super heavy-lift launch vehicle.
尽管 当三个一级火箭都回收使用的时候
Although, when all three cores are reused,
它的运载能力大概有30吨
its payload capability is more like 30 tons.
最后 则是航天飞机
And lastly, the Space Shuttle which,
如果你把航天飞机的轨道器作为它的有效载荷的一部分
if you include the orbiter as part of its payload capability,
它技术上可以把122.5吨送入轨道
it could technically put 122.5 tons into orbit.
也许需要马上指出的是 用同样的逻辑
I should probably point out real quick, by that same logic,
如果包括了SLS的芯级
if you included, say, the core stage of the SLS,
在一定的配置下 它也是能入轨的
which can get into orbit if they wanted it to,
按照这种说法 会使得它的有效载荷能力增加80吨
that would in that same way add another 80 tons to its payload capacity.
但是航天飞机跟这个不同
But the Shuttle was just a different beast,
某种程度上需要把轨道器当作入轨的有效载荷
and you kind of in some ways had to factor in the orbiter as payload that went orbital,
但实际上 可以部署的有效载荷质量真的只有大概27吨
but the actual, deployable payload capacity was really only about 27 tons.
尽管有太空梭C方案可以让它变为超重型火箭 但是 好吧(笑)
Although there was a proposed shuttle C to make it super heavy, but, okay (chuckles)
跑题了 我们继续吧
tangent, let's keep going.
如果人类想要尽快地返回月球
So if humans are to return to the moon ASAP,
或者说是要前往火星
or especially if we're to get to Mars,
我们绝对需要大量的运力
we absolutely need to have some serious capabilities.
当然 这些任务都是我们期待已久的
Of course, I think we're long overdue for these kinds of missions.
我想让人类以4K的画质重返月球
I want humans on the moon again, in 4k!
实际上 用8K也没问题
Actually, let's make is 8k.
只要把MKBHD和他的相机送到那里
Let's just send MKBHD up there with some of his cameras.
在我们开始讲关于SLS和Starship的事实之前
Now before we get started with SLS and Starship facts,
万一你是真的两耳不闻窗外事
in case you've been living under a rock,
NASA正在致力于通过阿尔忒弥斯计划重返月球
we are currently working on getting back to the moon with NASA's Artemis program,
大量的工作 资金和目标都展开了
and a substantial amount of work, funds and goals have been laid out.
所以在这个视频里 你会听到许多阿尔忒弥斯的名字
So during this video you'll hear Artemis thrown around quite a bit.
尽管我们也可以把月球轨道门户这个绕月空间站和阿尔忒弥斯混在一起讲
Although we could lump in the upcoming Space Station around the moon, Gateway, into Artemis,
但是这期只关注SLS火箭和猎户座飞船
we're really just going to focus on the SLS rocket, the Orion capsule,
还有载人着陆系统
and the Human Lander System.
毋庸置疑的是 SLS对于阿尔忒弥斯计划的地位相当于土星五号对阿波罗计划的地位
Which to be clear, SLS is to Artemis as Saturn V was to the Apollo program.
而现在 月球轨道门户将不会参与到最初的一到两次载人登月当中
And right now, the Gateway is being skipped for the first crewed lunar landing or two
而尽管很多事情都在为月球轨道门户酝酿和进行中
and although a lot of things are drawn up and in progress for Gateway,
我们只关注于月球着陆以及直接为此开发的设备
we're just going to focus on landing on the moon and the hardware that's directly involved in that.
SLS和猎户座的历史
[放松的音乐]
[relaxed music]
在对比两个火箭之前 要先澄清一些事实
We're gonna set some records straight here before we pit these two rockets head-to-head,
因为我觉得很多人有错误的看法
because I think a lot of people have the wrong idea
在NASA怎么以及为什么一开始就追求SLS和猎户座的方案
when it comes to how and why NASA pursued SLS and Orion in the first place,
以及这是如何融入到阿尔忒弥斯计划中的
and how they fit into the Artemis program.
在哥伦比亚航天飞机(2003)的惨剧之后
After the Space Shuttle Columbia tragedy,
NASA开始重新思考它的下一步计划
NASA started to rethink it's next steps
并且开始寻求一个能替代航天飞机的近地轨道(航天器)的方案
and began looking to a low Earth orbit replacement to the shuttle
并且开始决定要进行深空探测
and also started to set its sights on deep space exploration
为了做到这些 需要建造一个大火箭
and needed to build a big rocket in order to do so.
NASA最初的版本是星座计划
NASA's original vision was the Constellation program,
这是一个替代航天飞机的载人运输系统
which would be a crew transportation replacement for the Shuttle
这就是战神一火箭 还有一个深空版叫战神五火箭
with the Ares I and a new deep space rocket called Ares V.
在2009年Augustine委员会报告指出这个项目的缓慢进度和巨大超支之后
After slow progress and massive cost overruns pointed out in the 2009 Augustine Commission report,
星座计划最终取消了
the Constellation program wound up being canceled.
所以 2010年NASA授权法案指导NASA开发太空发射系统(SLS)
So the NASA Authorization Act of 2010 directed NASA to develop a Space Launch System
SLS可以写到70到100吨的载荷到近地轨道 而改进版可达130吨以上
capable of lifting 70 to 100 tons to low Earth orbit and evolvable to 130 tons or more.
火箭必须能够发射猎户座载人飞船
The vehicle must be able to lift the Orion Crew Vehicle
因为它的发展到目前为止就是为了配合猎户座飞船
since its development was so far along
还有就是NASA被要求尽可能地和现有的伙伴进行合作
and NASA was required to work with existing partners when available.
我们知道 NASA
As we know, NASA,
没有把战神一火箭当作近地轨道的火箭进行使用
instead of an Ares 1 low Earth orbit vehicle,
而是最后通过商业伙伴对国际空间站进行货物运输
ended up hiring commercial partners to send cargo
最终将会转变为通过商业载人计划对国际空间站进行载人运输
and eventually crew to the ISS with the Commercial Crew Program,
而NASA的工作则是建造更为专一性的火箭
and NASA was tasked with a more focused and leaner rocket.
这个想法是更快更有效地推出大型火箭
The thought was to roll out a massive rocket quickly and efficiently,
正如指示中所要求的那样 需要在2016年12月31日之前开始运营这枚火箭(笑哭)
as their directive required the vehicle to be operational by December 31st, 2016. (chuckles) (sighs)
NASA进行了品质因数的分析
NASA performed a figures of merit analysis
并把范围缩小到5种不同的火箭
and narrowed it down to five different variations of a launch vehicle.
有些看起来很不错
Some of them were getting pretty exciting,
譬如10米宽的芯级直径和富氧预燃分级燃烧循环发动机
with a 10-meter wide core diameter and oxygen-rich staged combustion engines.
分析对这些选项的评估指标为 55%的(可负担的)价格因素 25%的时间因素
The analysis weighed the options of affordability being 55%, schedule 25%,
10%的性能因素 10%的可行性因素
performance 10% and programmatic 10%.
NASA最终把项目落实为SLS
NASA landed on what we now know as the SLS,
虽然SLS和战神五号看起来非常像
and although SLS and Ares V look very similar,
但实际上SLS是相当于从头设计
SLS was actually a fairly blank slate design,
但是它肯定从DIRECT那个火箭方案上借鉴了不少东西
but it definitely took cues from a rocket proposal called DIRECT
这就意味着SLS肯定将严重依赖于航天飞机遗留下来的部件和设施
in which SLS would lean heavily on the literal leftover parts and facilities from the Space Shuttle
作为一个快速简便的方法 通过建造原型的方法来试验有史以来建造的最强大的火箭
as a quick and easy way to prototype and test out the most powerful rocket ever built.
和我们今天所知的商业载人计划不同
Unlike the Commercial Crew Program we know today,
NASA将继续和航天飞机的承包商们一起合作
NASA would continue to work with the contractors from the Shuttle
使用熟悉的成本加成合同的拨款方案
using the familiar cost-plus contracting funding scheme
这就基本意味着 我们给你这些钱 你把它给我搞定
which basically means, Here's how much money we're going to give you to get it done,
但是我们也会接受那些账单 当预算超支的时候
but we'll also pick up the bill on anything that goes over budget.
2011年以来SLS每年的拨款都在15亿美元左右
With funding hovering around 1.5 billion for SLS development per year since 2011
还有每年超过10亿美元多一点的猎户座飞船
and the Orion Capsule receiving a little more than one billion a year,
确保承包商有很多的资源来实现它们
the contractors were assured to have plenty of resources to make it happen,
但同时是在不超出NASA实际预算范围的情况下
but while staying within a realistic NASA budget
也就是和航天飞机时代的预算水准持平
which matched the funding levels during the Shuttle era.
但伴随着成本加成合同的问题则是
But the problem with cost-plus contracting is
它很难激励承包商不超支 尤其是不超时
it offers very little incentive to remain on budget or especially on schedule.
事实上 不按时完成计划意味着承包商能拿到更多钱
In fact, timeline slips literally means more money for the contractors,
还有SLS的主承包商
and the prime contractor for SLS,
也就是波音将会为这个项目收到最多的钱
Boeing, set to receive the most money for the project.
虽然NASA给它的承包商进行了绩效评价
Although NASA does performance reviews of their contractors,
对于某些承包商而言 这种仔细审查还是容易了一些
they've been scrutinized for being too easy on some of them,
之后再说这件事
more on that later.
所以 为了让一些承包商 员工 还有国会议员们开心
So in order to keep some of those contractors, employees, and members of congress happy,
让火箭的遗产与航天飞机紧密联系在一起
keeping the rocket's heritage close to the Space Shuttle
至少是这么想的 这样就会确保资金还是会继续会拨给航天飞机的承包商
ensured that funds would continue to be appropriated to Shuttle contractors, or so the thought was.
因此尽管SLS确实看起来像是个巨型的没有机翼的航天飞机
So although SLS does literally seem like a giant wingless space shuttle,
但是火箭还是进行了若干提高性能的改进
it's actually had many changes to make the vehicle have higher performance
同时它会比航天飞机的零件成本低
and lower costs than Space Shuttle's parts.
接下来会快速概括它的改进
Here's a quick rundown on the changes.
SLS会有一个五段的固体火箭助推器
The SLS will have five-segment solid rocket boosters,
而不是航天飞机使用的四段的那种
as opposed to the four-segment SRBs the Space Shuttle had,
同时也没有任何用于回收的设备 以及一个重新设计过的塞子
lacking any recovery hardware and featuring a redesigned plug
让碎屑出来
that keeps squirrels and stuff out of it,
重新设计后 碎屑不会在点火时伤害到RS-25的喷管
with the redesign ensuring debris won't potentially damage the nearby RS-25 nozzles on ignition.
芯一级 虽然看起来像是航天飞机的外储罐
The core stage, which, although it looks like a Space Shuttle's external fuel tank,
实际上除了颜色和8.4m直径以外 就没什么共同点了
there's virtually nothing in common with the external fuel tank other than its color and its 8.4-meter diameter.
它采用了全新的铝材 AL 2219
It uses a new aluminum, AL 2219,
不同的结构和焊接技术
different construction and welding techniques,
甚至不同的喷涂泡沫
and even a different spray foam.
人们肯定倾向于认为这只是个拉长的外储罐
People definitely tend to think it's literally a stretched external fuel tank,
这也包括我 但再说下 这之中真的完全不一样
me included, but again, it shares almost nothing in common,
这主要是因为SLS的罐顶承受来自上方的结构负载
mostly because SLS will have structural loads going down through the top of the tank
而不是(航天飞机外储罐那样)承受侧面的负载
as opposed to hanging off the side of the tank.
而RS-25自从航天飞机时代以来 已经改进了不少
The RS-25s have been tweaked quite a bit since the Space Shuttle
它们增加了推力 从104.5%到109% 在紧急情况下甚至能达到111%
and have increased their power output from 104. 5% to 109%, or 111% in an emergency.
但同样 就像固体助推器一样
But again, just like the SRBs,
SLS上的RS-25D和以后的RS-25E衍生型当然不会进行回收
the RS-25D and later the RS-25E variants will of course not be recovered on SLS.
顺便提个有趣的东西
Just a fun side note,
这些数字都是基于原来的海平面额定推力1600kN计算而来
those percentage numbers are based on the original rated thrust of 1.6 meganewtons at sea level.
在航天飞机主发动机的一些改进之后
After some tweaks in the Space Shuttle's main engines,
它们最终能超出航天飞机时期的原本的设计推力
they wound up being able to be throttled up beyond their original design during the Shuttle's program
并且在SLS时期更进一步
and are being pushed even further with SLS.
另外一个节省资金 加速计划的决定是
Another cost-saving and timeline-helping decision
SLS一开始就用几乎是ULA的Delta 4和Delta 4重型火箭的上面级
was to initially fly the SLS with quite literally the upper stage from ULA's Delta IV and Delta IV Heavy
也就是Delta低温二级 或者说DCSS
known as the Delta Cryogenic Second Stage, or DCSS,
只不过进行了修改来搭配在8.5米宽的芯级上面
only it's been modified to fit on top of the 8.5-meter wide core stage,
有着不同的氢气罐 和更多的RCS(反推力系统)燃料
have different hydrogen tanks, and more reaction control fuel.
这种配置被称为临时低温推进分级 或者说ICPS
This configuration is known as the Interim Cryogenic Propulsion Stage, or ICPS.
SLS计划有一个更强的上面级叫做探索上面级
SLS is intended to have a much more powerful upper stage known as Exploration Upper Stage,
这被认为是SLS Block 1B的升级部分 让SLS的运载能力更为强大
which is considered to be part of the Block 1B upgrade and makes SLS much more capable.
接下来 我们需要说说猎户座飞船
Next, we need to talk about the Orion capsule.
在阿尔忒弥斯任务中 它位于整个火箭的最顶端
It sits on top of this whole vehicle for the Artemis missions.
猎户座飞船是一个相当传统的载人飞船
The Orion Capsule is a fairly traditional crew capsule
在某种程度上 它只是一个放大的新版阿波罗飞船
and in some ways is a newer and embiginated version of the Apollo capsule.
但是 尽管看起来类似
But although it looks quite similar,
它比看上去要大得多
it's a lot bigger than it might appear.
直径上面 对比阿波罗的3.9米 它有5米
At five meters wide versus the Apollo capsule's 3.9 meters wide,
达到了很不错的9立方米的容积
and sporting an impressive nine cubic meters of volume,
对比阿波罗飞船的6.2立方米 这个空间挺大的 能够容纳6个宇航员
compared to 6.2 cubic meters, it'll be quite a bit roomier and capable of up to six astronauts,
尽管对于阿尔忒弥斯任务而言 它只会携带4名宇航员 而阿波罗只带了三个
although it'll probably only fly four for the Artemis missions, versus Apollo's three,
不过阿波罗技术上能带5个宇航员
which could technically fit five.
好吧 很勉强
Well, barely.
猎户座以前曾被称为载人探索飞行器
The Orion capsule used to be called the Crew Exploration Vehicle
这是它在星座计划时期研发中的名字
when it was in development for the Constellation program.
但是它已经改变了不少 并且拥有另一个节省成本的措施
But it has changed quite a bit and now features another cost savings measure,
这就是基于欧空局的自动运载飞船改进而来的服务舱
which is a service module based on ESA's Automated Transfer Vehicle.
但是 我们仍需要提到一个这批航天器中的新东西
But one thing we need to mention that's still new to this whole line-up,
而且仍在研发中的
and it's still in progress,
对于阿尔忒弥斯计划着陆于月球上而言绝对是需要的
and is definitely required for the Artemis program to land on the moon,
实际上那就是月球着陆器
and that is of course the actual lunar lander.
这也就是今天这个主题的来源
And that brings us to today.
到目前为止 我们所讨论过的东西
So far, everything we've talked about and discussed
只是通过SLS和猎户座飞船载人抵达绕月轨道
is only capable of getting humans into lunar orbit with SLS and Orion,
[麻麻快看，没有着陆器！]
SLS Block 1还没有能力一块儿将月球着陆器带过去
because there really still isn't the capability to also carry up a lunar lander with SLS Block 1,
[SLS会部署13个立方星在月球转移轨道进入后]
甚至是升级版的Block 1B
or even the upgraded Block 1B.
但是 NASA已经为阿尔忒弥斯计划正式选择了三个非常 非常不同的月球着陆器
But NASA has officially selected three very, very different lunar landers for the Artemis program,
而且每个提供商都需要在2021年前拟定它们的着陆器前往月球的方法
and each one has until 2021 to draw up exactly how they'll get their landers to the moon.
你知道的 有些方案可能最终会
You know some proposals could actually wind up
使用升级版的SLS也就是Block 1B来和猎户座一起发射它们的登月舱
still sending modules alongside Orion in the upgraded Block 1B SLS.
但是为了到达月球 对于阿尔忒弥斯3任务而言 将使用一枚SLS Block 1
But to get to the moon for Artemis 3, which will use a Block 1 SLS,
发射着陆器得需要一个单独的商业火箭
the lander will need to fly on a separate commercial rocket,
或者两个 三个 甚至另外一个SLS
or two, or three, or another SLS,
这将取决于这个登月器最后有多大了
depending on how big this thing ends up being,
因为阿尔忒弥斯的设备很大
because Artemis hardware is big.
阿尔忒弥斯的这部分与商业载人计划的关系联系得更紧密 相比于SLS和猎户座而言
This portion of Artemis is a lot closer to the Commercial Crew Program than it is to SLS and Orion.
NASA有一组需求
NASA has just a set of requirements,
但是让承包商拿出方案
but is letting the contractors put out proposals,
某种程度上这么做能有着惊人的速度和野心
and doing so in a way that's incredibly quick and ambitious
尽最大的可能进行2024年的载人登月
in the best attempt to get humans on the moon by 2024.
NASA将不会像SLS和猎户座那样拥有以及运营这个飞船
NASA will not own and operate the spacecraft like they do for SLS and Orion.
所以 这是否意味着
So this does mean
对于阿尔忒弥斯计划的每次载人任务 至少需要两枚火箭到达月球
that we will need at least two rockets per crewed mission to the moon for the Artemis program,
甚至三个或者四个
likely even three, maybe even four.
所以 我们会在下个视频讨论更多的载人登月系统
So we'll talk more about the options the Human Lander Systems proposals could use in the next video
当我们去研究NASA的其他选项时
when we look at what other options NASA has,
如果他们只是为了Starship和其他商业选项而完全取消了SLS
if they just full blown canceled SLS in favor of Starship and other commercial options.
那么 让我们来谈谈Starship
So, let's talk about Starship.
Starship的历史
[放松的音乐]
[relaxed music]
如果你是第一次听说Starship 或者SpaceX
If you're new to the scene of Starship, or SpaceX,
你可能不知道这个项目实际上起源于很早的阶段
you might not realize how far back this thing actually goes.
基本上 在SpaceX刚建立时
Basically, since SpaceX started,
就有关于BFR或者大猎鹰火箭的说法了
there's been talks of doing a BFR, or a Big Falcon Rocket.
而且 与SLS不同
And, unlike SLS,
研制从一开始就没怎么公开出来
the actual engineering and development had mostly been behind closed doors since the early days.
而且真的 在SpaceX建立之前
And really, going back before SpaceX's start,
推进系统的工程师和一号员工 Tom Mueller
propulsion engineer and employee #1, Tom Mueller,
曾经在他的高能火箭俱乐部 反作用研究社区里建造过一个BFR火箭发动机
had built a BFR rocket engine in his high-powered rocket club, Reaction Research Society.
没错 这个命名方案来自于毁灭战士的武器BFG
And yes, the naming scheme does stem from Doom's BFG.
有趣地是 Tom的BFR发动机是一个针栓喷注器的发动机 目标能达到4.536吨的推力
Fun side note, Tom's BFR engine was a pintle injector engine that was targeting 10, 000 pounds of thrust.
而且Tom和David Crisalli进行比赛
And Tom was facing off against David Crisalli,
而David Crisalli做了一个更加传统的平面喷注器
who built a more traditional flat-face injector.
Tom的设计获胜了 并且最终某种程度上成为了梅林发动机的原型
Tom's design won out and eventually kind of became the basis for the Merlin engine.
但是BFR的火箭完全没有得到公众的注意 直到2012年左右
But the BFR vehicle didn't really gain any public notice until around 2012
当马一龙提到了一个巨型火箭 叫火星殖民运输船
when Elon would mention a huge rocket dubbed Mars Colonial Transporter
以后SpaceX公司会把它加入进来
that SpaceX would add to their lineup.
但就在这时
But at this time,
SpaceX公司仍然是一个相对较小的公司
SpaceX was still a relatively small company,
在那时 仅仅发射了三枚猎鹰9火箭
only having launched three Falcon 9s to date.
在那之后 关于猎鹰X的谣言满天飞
After that rumors were swirling about a Falcon X,
还有重型猎鹰X 和猎鹰XX会成为SpaceX下一代巨型火箭的说法
Falcon X Heavy, and Falcon XX rocket that would be their next mega rockets.
直到2016年在墨西哥瓜达拉哈拉举行的国际宇航大会
It wouldn't be until 2016 at the International Aeronautical Congress in Guadalajara, Mexico
实际上大家才真的摸清SpaceX在做什么
that the world would really get a sense for what SpaceX was actually working on.
没错 就是那个超级怪异的新闻发布会上 每个人都在问这滑稽的问题
And yes, that was that super weird press conference where everyone asked ridiculous questions.
好吧 不是每个人
Well, not everyone.
你好 马一龙 我是Tim Dodd
Hello, Elon, Tim Dodd here,
Spaceflight Now的每日宇航员
the Everyday Astronaut with Spaceflight Now.
你说它会带着100名乘客入轨 然后在轨加注3到5次
You show it going into orbit with the 100 passengers and then refueling it three to five times,
然后进行火星转移轨道进入
and then doing your Mars injection.
- 对  - 这就是计划中的吗
- Right. - Is this the plan,
或者是会有一个加满燃料的IBT 或者MCT一类的东西
or is it to have a fully-fueled IBT, or MCT, or whatever,
然后再让乘客上去？
and then put passengers on board?
或者你可以跟我说一点儿这个过程中的细节吗？
Or can you tell me a little bit about that process?
- 好
- Yeah.
- 马一龙展示出的这个计划显得很狂暴
- The plans Elon showed were properly ludicrous,
ludicrous这里双关特斯拉的狂暴模式ludicrous mode
甚至是残暴
maybe even plaid,
plaid mode也是特斯拉即将推出的新模式
世所未见的事
something the world had never seen legitimately proposed.
一个完全可重复使用的 12米宽 122米高的火箭
A fully reusable, 12-meter wide, 122-meter tall rocket
一级有着42个全流量分级燃烧循环的液氧甲烷发动机
with 42 full-flow staged combustion methane-powered rocket engines on its first stage,
然后二级有着六个真空引擎和三个海平面引擎
then six vacuum engines and three more sea level engines on the upper stage,
以及先进的碳复合结构
and advanced carbon composite construction,
高达300吨的疯狂的有效载荷能力
and sporting a nutty 300-ton payload capacity.
它被称为行星际运输系统
It was known as the Interplanetary Transportation System.
2016年以后我们看到每年都有些改进
After 2016 we saw some tweaks year-to-year,
其中最大的变化就是不停地变化
with the biggest change actually being an unbeginning change
这种变化体现在火箭的直径突然缩水到9米 而它的运载能力也随之缩水
when suddenly the rocket shrunk to a nine meters in diameter and the capability shrunk with it.
这一次 SpaceX又开始叫它BFR了
Around this time, SpaceX started calling it BFR again
并宣布计划搭载日本的亿万富翁 前泽友作进行一次绕月旅行 叫亲爱的月亮
and announced plans to send Japanese billionaire, Yusaku Maezawo, on a trip around the moon for dearMoon.
但也许另一个大的变化是决定
But maybe another big change was the decision
不再使用碳复合材料而是使用不锈钢
to shift away from carbon composite construction and instead utilize stainless steel.
然后这个Starship的名字终于出现了
Then the name Starship finally came into existence.
而且 为了不被混淆
And, not to be confusing,
整个系统被称为Starship
the entire system is called Starship,
但是它的二级也叫这个名字
but so is the upper stage on its own.
一级火箭被称为超重型(助推器)
The booster is called Super Heavy.
所以 我们也可以粗略地将Starship称之为Starshp和超重型的组合体
So we can loosely say Starship meaning Starship and Super Heavy,
但我们也可能只是讨论它的上面级
but we could also just be talking about the upper stage.
有点像是你指着一块玉米说
Kind of like how you can point to corn and say,
嘿 看那是玉米 如果它不在玉米棒子上 而是在碗里
Hey look, that's corn. If it's off the cob and in a bowl,
你还是叫它玉米 但当它在棒子上的时候
you'll still call it corn, but when it's on the cob,
你或许可以说这是棒子上的玉米粒儿
you might say it's corn on the cob.
(笑) 你肯定会发现我是来自爱荷华州的 对吧
(chuckles) God, you can tell I'm from Iowa, can't you?
在2019年 SpaceX公司召开新闻发布会
In 2019, SpaceX held a press event
在德州博卡奇卡Starship全尺寸实体模型的前面 这个实体模型后来也被称为一号机
in front of a full size Starship mock-up prototype in Boca Chica later known as Mark 1.
至此 改设计的迭代是越来越少了
By this point, the design was iterating less and less,
而现在二级部分只有两个翼面 像是巨型的气动阻力板一样
and now the upper stage was to have only two fins that act like giant air brakes.
现在我已经做了个视频说明为什么他们喜欢用两个翼面而不是三个
Now I already did a video explaining the reasons why they likely went to two fins instead of three,
b23.tv/BV1ha4y1t73R
youtu.be/hsul-GE4XiA
这是个有趣的视频
and it's a fun video.
但是 这几乎让我们对Starship有了新的认识
But that pretty much gets us up to speed on Starship,
因为大部分开发工作都在幕后进行 只被SpaceX说明
since most of the development had been behind closed doors and on SpaceX's own terms.
我觉得现在是一个很好的时机去审视这两个项目的进展情况
I think now would be a good time to go through the progress of these two programs,
加上已经建造出来的东西
add up what exactly has been built,
看看我们能否更好地了解他们截然不同的设计理念
and see if we can get a better sense of their wildly different design philosophies.
SLS / 猎户座和Starship的进度和清单
[放松的音乐]
[relaxed music]
这就是我这段时间以来想做的那部分
So this is a segment I've wanted to do for a while.
Starship的怀疑者会指着所有炸毁的测试体然后说
Skeptics of Starship will point to all the blown up test articles and say,
你看 它们甚至不能造出一个储罐
See, they can't even build a tank,
而SLS的怀疑者称
while skeptics of SLS say,
十年过去了 什么都没发生
It's been a decade and nothing has happened.
那么 让我们列举出所有建造好的设备
So let's lay out all the hardware that's been built.
这会是非常全面的
This will be pretty comprehensive,
但不会覆盖到所有的东西
but not a full, complete list of absolutely everything,
但至少会列举出那些主要的里程碑事件
but we'll at least list out the major milestone things,
从SLS和猎户座开始
starting with SLS and Orion.
已经有比你想象得多的设备建造和测试完了
there's quite a lot more hardware that's been completed and tested than you might think.
到目前为止 我们已经看到了超过12个猎户座用在了战神1-X 不同的中止测试
So far we've seen over a dozen Orions be used between Ares 1-X, different abort tests,
实体模型和溅落测试中
mock-ups and drop test units.
2014年进行过一次大部分功能完整的真的猎户座返回舱的飞行
There's been a mostly feature complete flight of a legit Orion capsule in 2014
左边的图有点小问题，EFT-1没带服务舱，只带了一个服务舱的结构模型
也就是EFT-1 在Delta 4重型的顶部(进行发射)
on top of a Delta IV Heavy for EFT-1.
我当时在场 绝对令人难以置信
I was at that mission, and it was absolutely incredible.
还有就是SLS全尺寸氢燃料储箱的测试
There's been a test of a full-size hydrogen tank of SLS
在2019年于马歇尔太空中心 储罐承受了260%倍额定的结构负载 还持续了5个多小时
that lasted over five hours at 260% of its structural rating at Marshall Space Center in 2019.
为阿尔忒弥斯1任务 也就是SLS和猎户座完整测试准备的设备
All of the hardware for the first all-up test of SLS and Orion for the Artemis 1 mission
已经几乎准备好进行最终组装了
is pretty much ready for final assembly.
芯一级现在在试验台上准备进行全时长的静态点火
The core stage is currently on the test stand preparing to do a full duration static fire,
固体助推器的5个分段都准备好要组装了
the five segments of each SRB are ready to be stacked,
发射中止系统已经准备好了
the launch abort system is ready,
真正的猎户座返回舱已经完成了所有测试
the actual Orion capsule has finished all of its testing
并且返回了肯尼迪航天中心 等待即将到来的绕月任务
and is back at Kennedy Space Center awaiting its upcoming launch around the moon.
临时低温上面级已经准备好并且等待了多年
The Interim Cryogenic Propulsion Stage has been ready to go for years,
猎户座服务舱准备好了
the Orion service module is ready,
几乎所有阿尔忒弥斯的设备都完成了
literally all of the hardware for Artemis I is completed
并且完成了测试 接下来就是组装了
and finishing up testing and then integrations.
总共有16个RS-25D
In total there's 16 RS-25Ds,
其中四个要集成到芯一级上面
four of which are currently integrated onto the core stage,
而另外14个之前进行过航天飞机的发射
and 14 of those RS-25s previously flew on Shuttle missions.
有足够的分段来制作16个固体火箭助推器
There's enough Solid Rocket booster segments to make up 16 boosters.
还有4个RL-10发动机可以用于上面级
There's also four more RL-10 engines ready to be used for upper stages.
而现在 生产线和工艺流程都到位了
And now that the manufacturing lines and practices are in place,
阿尔忒弥斯2任务的部件正在结合
parts for Artemis II are coming together,
包括液氧储罐 液氢储罐 储罐过渡段
including the LOX tank, hydrogen tank, intertank,
级间段 发动机舱
forward skirt, engine section,
猎户座返回舱的加压舱 猎户座的服务舱
the pressure vessel for Orion, its service module,
隔热板 逃逸塔
the heat shield, launch abort tower,
还有些其他的设备也到位了
and other bits of hardware, too.
当然 如前所述
And of course, as mentioned,
RS-25和助推器段也是足够的
the RS-25s and booster segments are complete, too.
但是 这还不是全部
But that's not all.
阿尔忒弥斯3的设备也已经在做了
Artemis 3 hardware is also coming together already too,
包括猎户座的部件 SLS的液氢储罐
including parts of Orion, the SLS hydrogen tank,
服务舱的部件
parts of the service module,
再说一遍 还有那些发动机和固体火箭助推器
and again the engines and solid rocket motors.
这就是目前或者说过去十年完成的东西
This is what's been accomplished and completed throughout the last decade-ish.
那么这和Starship的进度如何比较呢
So how's that compared to Starship's progress?
Starship的进度是非常不同的
Starship's progress is very different.
猛禽发动机的研发开始于2012年左右
The Raptor engine started development around 2012,
从那时起 我们知道这些东西已经被建造和测试完了
and since then, here's a list of what we've seen built and tested.
迄今为止 已经建好了超过26个猛禽发动机
To date, there's been over 26 Raptor engines built,
它们中的许多现在还处在零件状态
many of which are in pieces now,
只有一小部分现在真的能飞
and likely only a handful that are truly flight capable at this point.
但是这个数字变得很快
But that number is changing rapidly,
因为SpaceX几乎是只在2019年就把它们都制造出来了
as SpaceX has cranked out pretty much all of those in just 2019 alone.
如果我们忽略了碳复合材料的研发进度和它的试验品
And if we ignore the progress and the test articles for anything carbon composite
以及或者12米直径的Starship的设备
and/or 12-meter diameter Starship,
再说一遍 几乎所有列出来的东西都是在去年造好的
again, almost everything we're about to list was built within the last year.
从Starshopper开始
Starting with Starhopper,
而这是唯一能飞的Starship原型机
which is the only Starship prototype to really fly,
虽然说是为了试飞而制造的 至少飞了两次
well on purpose, at least, with two flights,
一次是20米飞行 另一次是150米飞行
a 20-meter hop and a 150-meter hop.
然后我们看到了全尺寸原型一号机的组装
Then we saw the Mark 1 full-scale prototype come together.
也在那时 SpaceX在 佛罗里达州可可建造了一个类似的原型机
At the same time, SpaceX was building a similar prototype in Cocoa, Florida
这种方式可以让两个不同的团队在友谊赛中研究不同的施工方法
as a way for two different teams to work on different methods of construction in a friendly competition.
二号机 正如我们所知 现在遗弃在那里
Mark 2, as it was known, has since been abandoned and is still just hanging out there.
然后我们在2019年底看到两个团队合理完成并测试了一号原型机
Then we saw the two teams come together at the end of 2019 to finish and test the Mark 1 prototype,
测试失败了
which failed when testing,
某种程度上这个失败是能预测到的 因为他们开始了下一个原型机的制造
as was kind of expected because they were already working on the next one,
这个被称为序列号1(SN1)
which would be called SN1,
这时他们开始把命名的方式从几号机改成序列号几
and that's when they switched from the Mark to Serial Number nomenclature.
在这段时间 已经有三个非全尺寸的试验品对焊接工艺进行了测试
There's been three subscale pressure test articles that have tested the welds
以及在低温的情况下耐压的能力
and the ability to hold pressure at cryogenic temperatures around this time, too.
他们测试了SN1
They tested SN1,
某种程度上是内爆了 当它的底部掉下来时
which kind of imploded when its bottom fell off.
然后我们看到了SN3 因为不正确的测试程序 也失败了
Then we have SN3, which also failed due to improper testing procedures.
而且 正在这个视频制作的时候
And, as of the making of this video,
SN4已经完成 而SN5则是大步向前
SN4 is already complete and SN5 is well on its way.
如果我不断地尝试通过他们制造的新部件来更新这个愚蠢的动画
And if I keep trying to update this stupid animation with all the new parts they're making,
这个视频永远都做不出来
this video will never come out,
因为他们做这些东西实在是太快了
because they're just making them so quickly.
因此 换句话说 SpaceX已经造好并炸毁了
So in other words, SpaceX has built and blown up
比SLS 3倍多的储罐 在过去的半年里
three times more tanks in the last six months than SLS has built in the last six years.
而这正是我们看到的在制造 测试和整体理念的巨大的差异
And this is where we see the massive, massive differences in the building, testing, and overall philosophies.
再仔细研究下这里
Time to dig into this for a second.
Starship和SLS的设计理念
[令人振奋的音乐]
[upbeat music]
你现在也许已经知道这里面的设计理念差异
By now you've already probably got a really good sense of the design differences and philosophies
只要看看这两个项目发展的历史
just by seeing how these two programs have developed over time.
但是还有几件事真的能看出他们之间的巨大区别
But there's a few things that really, really drill in just how different they truly are.
那么 让我们从NASA的角度来看看
So let's start by putting ourselves in NASA's shoes.
NASA 被政府资助的机构
NASA, being government funded,
必须和私人赞助的私人公司有很多不同
has to do things quite a lot differently than a private company with private funding,
但这之中最关键的事情也许是他们真的不能冒很大的险
but perhaps the biggest thing they can't really do is take big risks.
当他们在建造一些巨大 复杂 且有野心的项目类似SLS这样的
When building something as massive, complex and ambitious as SLS,
你就真的需要说明几乎所有的东西
you really need to account for absolutely everything
在你给承包商发出指令之前
before you start sending out the instructions to the contractors.
如果你告诉你的承包商开始建造某个东西 而在计划中有了新的变化
If you start telling contractors to start building something and then something changes in the plan,
所有(改变前进行)的工作都将是徒劳的
all of that work is for naught.
而当你有着几十个承包商和若干公务员的时候 加剧了这种情况
And this compounds when you have dozens of contractors and government supporting employees
他们都依赖于对方及时地完成自己的那部分工作
all relying on each other to have their parts done on time.
想象一下一个关键组件延迟了一年
Imagine if a key part gets delayed a year.
支持这个系统的公务员该怎么办
What are the government employees supporting that system supposed to do?
你不能把他们解雇一年再让他们回来为项目工作吧
You can't just lay them off for a year and then bring them back onto the project,
他们会去找新的工作
they're gonna go find new work.
你不能给他们重新分配别的事干
You can't really reassign them to something else.
不像是推进系统工程师现在可以研究别的火箭去了
It's not like a propulsion engineer is now just going to move over to the other rocket
而这个火箭也是NASA现在正在研制的
NASA is currently working on.
在运行这种规模的项目时 每年都有很多固有的沉没成本
There's a lot of inherent costs per year that are sunk costs in running a program of this scale.
所以 尽管它本来就风险小 效率低
So, although it's inherently less risky and inefficient,
但对于多个承包商还是有个安全的网络 和遍布全国的太空中心
there's also a safety net for having multiple contractors and space centers spread throughout the country,
这些都会更加吸引国会
which massively helps make it more appealing to congress.
所以 尽管它是低效的
So, although it is inefficient,
它至少确保了项目的生存性 并且让它能持续地得到资助
it at least does help ensure the program survival and that it continues to be funded.
当你发现欧罗巴快船那事儿写进法律的时候 你就会发现这话太对了
And this is especially true when you realize that it's written into law that the Europa Clipper,
这个访问土星的卫星 土卫二欧罗巴的探测器 被立法授权了要使用SLS进行发射
a probe to Jupiter's moon, Europa, is legally mandated to fly on SLS.
关于这事儿最疯狂的地方也许在于
And perhaps most nutty about that fact is
是项目得到了2.5亿美元的资助
that $250 million has been added to the program
因为直到至少2025年都不会有SLS火箭
because there won't be an SLS rocket until at least 2025,
尽管这个探测器2023年就造好了
despite the probe being ready by 2023.
但是长远来看 这个法案能够确保SLS这个项目持续前进并得到资助
But in the long run, this law did help keep a program moving forward and being funded
特别是在这种不断换届的政府 充满变化的时代之下
during what could be very uncertain times with changing administrations.
显然现在这样很不理想
Now this obviously isn't ideal at all,
但如果你担心项目的生存能力
but if you're worried about program survivability
同时不只是让你的整个视野范围每四或八年就翻个180度
and not just having your entire vision shift 180 degrees every four to eight years,
无论好坏 这样做事就是游戏规则的一部分
doing things like this is just kinda part of the game, for better or worse.
但是别忘了 NASA的预算只有国家预算的0.5%
But don't forget, NASA's budget is only about half a percent of our national budget,
而载人航天项目甚至不到这其中的一半
and the human space flight programs aren't even half of that.
因此 在一般情况下 建造SLS的主要理念是提前计划 并减小风险
So in general, the primary philosophy of building SLS is to plan ahead and take little risks,
因为实在没有多少空间容许失败
because there really isn't much room to fail
在这种情况下 你必须向纳税人回答为什么他们的钱灰飞烟灭了
when you have to answer to the taxpayers why their money literally went up in smoke.
现在再对比下Starship
Now compare this to Starship.
Starship的发展得到的成果真的就是与它的从头开始这点密切相关
Starship development is literally about as blank slate as it gets.
SpaceX开始的时候不仅没有详细的蓝图
SpaceX started not with detailed blueprints,
而且真的就是从如何提问开始的
but quite literally started by just learning what questions to ask
如何框住他们火箭性能的需求
and how to frame the constraints of what their vehicle should do.
SpaceX最终得到了两个主要目标
SpaceX seems to have wound up on two main objectives.
一个是充分且迅速的重复使用
Be fully and rapidly reusable,
另一个则是有着足够大的运载能力能让人类登陆其他天体
and have a capability large enough to be useful in getting humans onto other celestial bodies.
这才是它的需求 然后倒着来设计
That's really about it, and then start to work backwards.
下一个能够回答这个问题的明确的项目是
The next most pinned down item that helps to answer
研发一个高效且能大量重复使用的发动机
that question is developing an engine that is efficient and massively reusable.
就像我那个讨论了SpaceX猛禽发动机的视频
Like I talked about in my video about SpaceX's Raptor engine,
一个甲烷驱动的全流量分级燃烧循环发动机
a methane powered full-flow staged combustion cycle engine,
能够完美地达到那些目标
fits the needs of those goals perfectly.
从那里开始 整个事情就像是一个巨大的游乐场一样
From there on, the whole thing is pretty much just a giant playground.
因此 当我们看到从碳纤维到不锈钢的突然而出人意料的转折时
Hence, when we saw the sudden and unexpected pivot from carbon fiber to stainless steel,
你就会知道只是开始飞行这件事对于SpaceX而言是多么重要
you get a sense of just how important it is for SpaceX to just start flying
这样他们才有一个可以迭代的起点
so they have a starting point to iterate on
这也就是马一龙解释说为什么这个转变是如此的重要
when you hear Elon explain why it was so important to make the switch.
- 以一般方法
- Taking the general approach of,
如如果设计花费的时间太长 那么它就是错误的
if a design is taking too long, the design is wrong,
因此 设计时必须进行修改 以加快进度
and therefore the design must be modified to accelerate progress.
- 对
- Right.
- 坚持设计是一个在高级的研发所作出的最基本的错误
- One of the most fundamental errors made in advanced development is to stick to a design
即便这只是一个过于复杂而不去尝试通过减少过程和部件(来简化它)的问题
even when it is very complicated and to not strive to delete parts and processes.
这是非常重要的
It's incredibly important.
所以这就是为什么改用钢 是因为(制造)先进的碳纤维耗时太长
So this is why the switch to steel was because the advanced carbon fiber was taking too long.
这就是为什么我们在那里看到了那么多随机性的事件
This is why we're seeing so many random things happening down there
也就是德克萨斯州 博卡奇卡 Starship的研发中
at Boca Chica, Texas with the development of Starship.
这就是为什么再去问他们未来的计划都有点蠢了
It's why it's kind of silly to even bother asking about future plans anymore,
当然了 我也是这个愚蠢的分子之一(笑)
which of course I'm as guilty of as anyone. (chuckles)
因为所有的东西都取决于现阶段的情况
Because everything depends on what's going to happen with the current step,
以后的发展将会取决于前一步的结果 等等
and the step in development after that will be based on the results of the previous step and etc etc.
这个理念类似于敏捷建模
It's a similar philosophy to something known as the agile model
这是软件开发的标准
which is standard in software development,
这很合理 因为马一龙原本的背景是软件
which makes sense because of Elon's original background in software.
基本上 你在第一步完成之前不需要进行第二步的工作
Basically, you don't work on step two until step one is done.
任何提前的规划可能会导致你必须要撤回之前所做的
Planning ahead any further and you're very likely going to have to just undo work.
那么这与SLS的理念完全相反
Now this is quite literally the opposite of SLS,
SLS的所有组成都需要一个确切的计划
where everything needs to have an exact plan
因为 如果你的火箭造得比蓝图上的要短3米
because, if you end up building the rocket three meters shorter than the blueprints,
突然间 你的整个地面支持系统也要进行更改了
all of a sudden your entire ground support system will change too,
顺便说一句 基本上SLS和它的移动发射塔已经发生了很多这样的事情
and by the way, pretty much this exact thing has basically happened with SLS and its mobile launch tower.
但是 Starship的所有东西还在考虑当中
But everything for Starship is still on the table at the moment.
我是指 我真的是看到他们是围着火箭造工厂 而不是反过来
I mean, we're literally seeing them build a factory around a rocket instead of vice versa.
坦率地说 这是非常危险的
And frankly, this is pretty risky.
但它也很容易做的
But it's also much easier to do,
因为SpaceX就是如此垂直整合的
because SpaceX is so vertically integrated,
这意味着在决策的变化并不会有其他更传统的方法产生的连锁反应大
meaning changes in decisions don't have nearly as big of a ripple effect as the other, more traditional methods.
但正如我们所知道的那样 会有更多的设备出现失败
But just know, we will see more hardware fail.
我们会看到一些失利 我们还有可能看到一些爆炸
We will see some setbacks, we will likely see explosions.
但是 它和SLS不一样 不仅是失败对它影响不大
But, unlike SLS, not only is it okay to fail,
而且这种成败皆可的预期 也可以作为一种方法来廉价快速地学习并建造原型机
it's halfway expected as a way to learn and prototype with lower cost and greater speed.
马一龙总是这么说过
Elon has said over and over in some way or another,
失败是可能发生的，如果你没失败过，那么是你不够创新 - 马一龙
这与苏联的设计理念非常类似
This is very similar to the Soviet Union's design philosophy.
基本上 尽可能廉价地建造某个事物
Basically, build something as cheap as possible,
测试一下 如果它炸毁
test it out, if it blows up,
[必须得承认，N-1火箭不是这个理念的最佳范例]
看看哪里出了问题 做出改进 再重复这一过程
see what went wrong, make improvements, repeat.
这在早期的太空竞赛当中肯定是帮了他们一把
And it definitely gave them a leg up in the space race during early development.
所以说要如果炸毁了那个一个月内造好的火箭
So say you blow up a rocket that you built in a month,
好吧 从中吸取教训
oh well, learn from it.
SpaceX建造另一枚火箭的速度 会比NASA加满燃料并点火测试一次SLS的速度更快
SpaceX will build another rocket in less time than it'll take NASA to fuel up and test fire the SLS once.
这就是设计理念中的巨大区别
And that's just simply a huge, huge difference in philosophies.
Starship对比SLS
[放松的音乐]
[relaxed music]
好吧 是时候把这俩火箭摞起来并排比比
Okay, I think it's time we really stack these rockets up side by side to help figure out
这样才能做到真正的对比
just how they really compare when we look at their nuts and bolts.
我们已经谈过了这两种火箭的尺寸
We've already touched on each vehicle's dimensions,
这就是它们在屏幕上的样子
so here they are again on screen.
现在 我们只会比较每个火箭的最初版本
For now, we'll compare some initial builds of each rocket,
因此这是SLS Block 1和Block 1B和现在Starship的粗糙版
so the Block 1 and Block 1B of SLS and the rough-ish version of Starship as it currently stands.
但可以肯定的是 Starship会改变很多(笑)
But definitely keep in mind that Starship will change (chuckles) a lot,
每造一个 几乎都会变几十处
pretty much every time one gets built for at least the first dozen or two.
但是如果Block 1B上线 SLS还可以改变一点
But SLS could also change a bit too if Block 1B goes online.
既然说到这儿了
But while we're at it,
让我放上土星五号和猎鹰重型
let's throw up the Saturn V and the Falcon Heavy
只是让我们有一些额外的视角来看待这些火箭 这样才能真正的比较
just so we have some extra perspective on how these vehicles really compare.
当今天它们站在这里 SLS是大 真的大
As they stand today, SLS is big, really big,
但Starship会是庞大无比的
but Starship will be huge.
现在 让我们来谈谈发动机及其燃料
Now let's talk engines and their fuels.
猎鹰重型拥有27个海平面梅林引擎
Falcon Heavy has 27 sea level Merlin engines
并在其上面级有一个真空优化的梅林发动机 使用RP-1燃料
and a single vacuum-optimized Merlin engine on its upper stage, which all run on RP-1.
然后就是土星五号 它第一级有五个F1引擎 使用RP-1燃料
Then there's the Saturn V, which had five F1 engines on its first stage that ran on RP-1,
在第二级有五个J2发动机
five J2 engines on the second stage,
以及第三级有一个J2发动机 都是用液氢燃料的
and a J2 on the third stage that ran on hydrogen.
我们知道 SLS有两个固体火箭推进器
As we know, SLS has two SRBs,
4个RS-25使用液氢燃料 并且Block 1其上面级只有一个RL-10B2
four RS-25s running on hydrogen, and the Block 1 has only a single RL-10B2 on its upper stage,
而Block 1B将有四个RL-10 都使用液氢燃料
and the Block 1B will have four RL-10s that all run on hydrogen.
最后 Starship中Super Heavy有37台猛禽引擎而Starship有差不多6台
Lastly, Starship has 37 engines on the Super Heavy booster and six-ish Raptor on Starship.
这个数字很可能发生变化
This number is very subject to change,
并且SpaceX这样做相对容易 是因为猛禽的发动机的尺寸小
and is relatively easy for SpaceX to do so because of the small size of the Raptor engine.
接下来 让我们来看看它们的起飞推力
Next let's look at their thrust at lift off.
与往常一样 这非常有趣
As always, this is pretty fun.
猎鹰重型在这里就是个宝宝 有22.8MN
The Falcon Heavy is the baby here at 22.8 meganewtons,
接着强力的土星五号有35.1
followed by the mighty Saturn V at 35.1,
然后SLS有39.1
then the SLS at 39.1,
最后 Starship将在这里称王 按照当前标准有72MN
and lastly, Starship will be the king here at 72 meganewtons as it currently stands.
现在 我们已经过了一遍其中部分火箭的近地轨道的运力
Now we've already gone over some of these rockets' low Earth orbit capabilities,
所以 让我们把SLS和Starship放回这里
so let's add SLS and Starship back into this.
请注意 我们将显示SLS Block 1及升级后Block 1B的运力
Now notice, we are going to be showing performance for SLS Block 1 and the Block 1B upgrade,
但它们近地轨道的运载能力几乎是相同的
but their low Earth orbit capabilities are virtually the same
因为它的芯级差不多在入轨后分离
since it's the core stage that pretty much drops them off into orbit.
但是现在让我们来展示它们能送多少质量到月球
But now let's show how much mass they can shoot off to the moon,
这又被称为月球转移轨道进入或TLI
otherwise known as a trans-lunar injection or TLI,
由于我们在这里谈论月球任务
since we're talking about lunar missions here anyway.
注意一下 这并不是一定要求火箭把载荷送入绕月轨道
Quick note, this isn't necessarily how much a vehicle can put into lunar orbit,
只是有多少质量它能飞掠月球
just how much it could shoot off to the moon.
你仍然需要你的飞船来进入绕月轨道(近月制动)
You still need to get into lunar orbit with your spacecraft.
在猎户座飞船或阿波罗飞船的情况下
In the case of Orion or Apollo,
这由服务舱完成
that's done with the Service module.
这是在技术上准确来说是-0.99的C3
And this is technically a C3 of -0.99 to be exact,
这用来衡量到达太空中特定点所需的特征能量
which is a measurement of the characteristic energy to get to a certain point in space.
猎鹰重型 当复用时
Falcon Heavy, when reused,
如果两个助推器和芯一级在无人船上降落 可以运载大约9吨到月球
can sling about nine tons to the moon if all three cores land downrange on drone ships,
或不复用时15吨左右
or about 15 tons when expended.
然后我们有土星五号 可以运送48.6吨到月球
Then we have the Saturn V that could send 48.6 tons to the moon.
然后 SLS Block 1可以运27.5吨
Then, SLS Block 1 can take 27.5 tons,
而1B可以运最高43吨
and the 1B can do up to 43 tons.
现在 你可能会问 为什么更强大的火箭比土星五号运往月球的质量还少？
Now, you might ask, "How can a more powerful rocket get less to the moon than the Saturn V?"
嗯 因为中间低温推进段对于这种规模的火箭来说太小了
Well, that interim cryogenic propulsion stage is seriously undersized for this size of rocket.
但奇怪的是 即使Block 1B有四个RL-10引擎的探索上面级
But oddly, even with the Block 1B and the four RL-10 powered Exploration Upper Stage,
SLS仍然只能运送43吨到月球
the SLS can still only send 43 tons to the moon,
所以这和土星五号的运力相比有些少了
so that's shy of what the Saturn V was capable of.
很坦率地说 这让我有点迷惑
Which, quite frankly, that's kinda baffling to me.
而Starship当谈及TLI时会有点令人困惑
And Starship is a little more confusing when it comes to TLI.
Starship自己不能进行TLI
Starship on its own cannot do a trans-lunar injection.
由于其巨大的120吨干质量
Because of its massive 120-ton dry mass,
没有重新加燃料的情况下拖着所有的自重一路去月球不太可行
lugging all of that dead weight all the way out the moon doesn't work out without it being refueled.
现在当然 在轨补加肯定是Starship计划的一部分
Now of course, in-orbit refueling is 100% part of the plan for Starship.
但是在即将到来的视频里我们会更多地谈论这部分
But we'll talk more about that more in an upcoming video
那时我会说说使用上面级的Starship对比在轨补加的Starship
where I'm gonna talk about Starship using a kick stage versus Starship refueling.
那么现在我们要研究一下这个难以描述的问题 看准咯
So now here's where we're going to go into a deep, deep rabbit hole, so hold on to your butts.
我们要讨论价格
We're gonna talk price,
这不是一件容易的事情 你会明白为什么
and this is not an easy thing to talk about, you'll see why.
你看到所有的数字都会被调整到等值2020年的美元
And all numbers you'll see are adjusted for 2020 US dollars.
让我们从我所谓的标签价开始
Let's start off with what I'm going to call the sticker price.
这是你大概可以买一发火箭的价格
This is the price you could presumably buy a launch.
现在我们是先忽略开发成本
For now we're kind of ignoring development costs
而只是发票上一发火箭的价格 如果有发票的话
and just what the invoice would be for a launch of said rocket.
不过我们很快会讨论开发成本 但现在 先不管这些东西
But we're going to get into the development costs in a second, but for now, just file these away.
而我们也只是去看火箭
And we're also only going to look at just the rockets,
不考虑上面的阿波罗或猎户座飞船
not the spacecraft like Apollo or Orion.
从猎鹰重型火箭开始 复用价格大约9000万起
Starting with Falcon Heavy at around 90 million when reused
不回收价格大约在1.5亿
and probably around 150 million when expended.
土星五号是12亿左右
The Saturn V was around 1.2 billion,
SLS Block 1和之后的Block 1B一旦生产稳定将是8.75亿
SLS Block 1 and the later Block 1B will be 875 million once production stabilizes.
和Starship 好吧马一龙声称他们发射只要2百万美元
And Starship, well, uh, Elon claims they can launch for two million.
但是让我们假设他们只要2百万
But let's assume they can do two million,
但一段时间他们会机智地要价一亿美元 直到市场价赶上Starship
but for a while they'd be smart to charge 100 million until the market catches up.
因此 让我们就把一亿美元当作更像是最坏的情况下的标价
So let's just throw 100 million out there as more of a worst case scenario sticker price.
现在有了这些数字
Now with these numbers,
我们可以算一个非常基础的美元对千克比值
we can do a very baseline dollar to kilogram ratio.
而且因为我们再次谈及月亮
And since we're talking about the moon again,
让我们只看要花多少钱
let's only look at how much it costs
也就是用各种火箭把一公斤东西通过TLI的方式送去月球
to send one kilogram to the moon on a trans-lunar injection for each of these vehicles.
猎鹰重型不论是回收或不回收大约10000$/kg
Falcon Heavy can get one kilogram to the moon for around $10,000 whether it's reused or expended.
随后 土星五号约25600$/kg
Then the Saturn V was about $25,600,
SLS Block 1以稳定生产状态最好的情况大约是31500$/kg
SLS Block 1 best case scenario with a stabilized production is around $31, 500,
但Block 1B看起来较好一点 要20000$/kg
but Block 1B looks quite a bit better at $20,000 per kilogram.
最后 Starship
And lastly, Starship.
现在记住 一次价值一亿美元的Starship发射并不能带着载荷进行TLI
Now remember, a single $100 million Starship launch can't get anything on a trans-lunar injection,
所以还需要额外发射两次Starship来补充燃料 各花费一亿美元
so it's going to take two additional launches to refuel it at an extra $100 million each
来运送156吨有效载荷进行TLI
in order to send 156 tons of payload on a trans-lunar injection,
最后这会耗资约2000$/kg
which would wind up costing about $2,000 per kilogram.
如果你看不出来
In case you couldn't tell,
我们在一种类似低估的方式评价Starship以免这估计太过乐观
we're kind of sandbagging Starship just in case it's way, way too optimistic.
而且即便如此 它仍然是图表中迄今为止最经济实惠的
And even so, it's still by far the most economical thing on the chart.
但这些初步的成本建立在大量的假设上
But these preliminary costs are taking a lot of assumptions.
还没考虑开发的成本
They don't really factor in development costs,
并且我们还有很多在预算和成本方面需要补充的东西
and we've still got a lot to cover on the topic of budgets and cost.
所以现在先不去考虑这些
So for now, just file this away,
因为在接下来的视频中 我们将真正把这些涉及到成本的麻烦玩意儿追查到底
because in the next video we'll really chase all the rabbit holes when it comes to costs.
总结
[令人振奋的音乐]
[upbeat music]
那么我们是如何来到这里的？
So how did we get here?
怎么会我们有两个完全不同的巨型火箭在同时上线？
How is it that we have two completely different super duper mega rockets going online at the same time?
我觉得历史是不言而喻的
I think the history kind of speaks for itself.
当NASA开始SLS的工作时
When NASA started working on SLS,
像Starship这种火箭的想法会是绝对可笑的
the thought of a rocket like Starship would've been utterly ludicrous.
我的意思是 即使今天 很多人都认为这是疯狂且可能失败的
I mean, even today, many people think it's insane and likely to fail.
但是Starship知道它做出来之前 很多人都会觉得它是不可能做出来的
But Starship is impossible until it's not.
然后 突然之间 所有的一切变了
And then, all of a sudden, literally everything changes.
而且不要忘了 NASA在SLS和猎户座上花了近10年的时间了
And don't forget, NASA has been working on SLS and Orion for nearly a decade.
如果SpaceX公司在2011年用Starship和NASA接洽
If SpaceX had approached NASA with Starship in 2011,
这就会像是尝试在1870年向农民出售一个GPS导航的
it would've been like trying to sell a farmer in 1870 a GPS-guided,
九升涡轮增压柴油发动机 四轨式 8RX 410型 John Deere拖拉机
nine-liter turbodiesel-powered four-track 8RX 410 John Deere tractor
有着无级变速器
with an infinitely variable transmission
和85cc位移集成液压泵 流速每分钟227升
and 85-cc displacement integrated hydraulic pump with 227 liters per minute of hydraulic flow,
空调和座椅加热
air conditioned and heated,
10英寸的触摸屏显示器和数字监视器
10-inch touchscreen displays and digital monitoring
而他们只希望给他们的马买个耕地的犁
when they were looking to purchase a plow for their horse.
他们仅仅只是不会相信你罢了(笑)
They just simply wouldn't have believed you. (chuckles)
哦各位 我又秀了我的爱荷华州身份 抱歉
Oh man, I showed my Iowa again, sorry.
NASA不知道多少次自己给自己下绊子
And NASA has had the rug pulled out from underneath them so many times,
这么多的项目起步
so many programs getting started,
甚至在这些项目有机会开始前
only to change direction and change hands 100 times
就改变了100次方向和负责人
before the program even has a chance to really get going.
因此NASA做了他们必须做的 采取安全保守的路线
So NASA did what they had to do, they took a safe, conservative route,
依靠现有的技术 合作伙伴和项目资金计划设计火箭
leaning on existing technologies, partners, and program funding schemes to lay out a rocket
所以不管如何这很难被取消
that would for better or worse have a hard time being canceled
因此他们可能至少在近50年来第一次拥有真正的深空能力
so they could at least have truly deep space capabilities for the first time in nearly 50 years.
因为我认为这才是其中最震撼的
Because I think that's the biggest shocker in all this.
这不是Starship
It's not Starship.
Starship正向人类走来
Humanity has Starship coming.
Starship是注定的 因为坦率地说 建造可完全重复使用的火箭这件事 是完全说得通的
Starship is destined, because frankly it makes sense to make a fully reusable rocket.
每个人都想要这样的火箭 每个人都希望这样做
Everyone wants that, everyone wants to do that,
没有人认为这是一个坏主意
no one thinks that's a bad idea,
没有人认为它永远 永远 永远不会发生
and no one thinks it's never, ever, ever going to happen.
但我认为 最让人惊讶的是这居然发生在
But I think the biggest surprise is that it would be almost 50 years
有能力将人送上月球的土星五号火箭出现的近五十年后
before there was a rocket capable of taking humans to the moon after the Saturn V.
如果你把这个事实告诉最后一个在月球上漫步的人 Gene Cernan
If you told that fact to the last person to walk on the moon, Gene Cernan,
在他1972年回地球时 说在2020年后还是没人回到月球
upon his return home in 1972 that no one will have returned to the moon by 2020.
他大概会把Buzz Aldrin拉过来给你的脸狠狠来一记
he probably woulda pulled a Buzz Aldrin and punched you right in the face.
Buzz Aldrin(巴兹奥尔德林)真对一个质疑他登月的人这么干了
直到市场转变 使得火箭技术成为可行的方案
It wasn't until the market shifted that rocket technology became achievable,
而这是由一小撮智慧又勇敢的人们 而不是国家带来的
not by nations, but by a small handful of brilliant and plucky individuals
这些人能够重新反思一切 开辟商业选项和机会
that could rethink everything and open up commercial options
而这些在之前并不存在
and opportunities that just simply didn't exist before.
我知道马一龙的人生目标是去火星
I know Elon's life goal is to get to Mars,
但在此期间 他更会完全改进人类进入太空的方式
but in the meantime, he'll have completely changed humanity's access to space for the better.
是的 甚至当你纳入火箭污染的因素
And yes, even when you factor in how much rockets pollute,
因为 相信我 我对此也已经做了非常 非常长的视频
because, trust me, I've already done a very, very long video on that, too,
b23.tv/BV1eE411c7ts
youtu.be/C4VHfmiwuv4
这是一个令人着迷的主题
which is a fascinating topic,
你绝对应该去看一眼
you should definitely have a watch.
为了去到火星 你需要一个完全复用的巨型火箭
In order to get to Mars, you need a fully reusable, massively capable rocket,
然后发现这个疯狂的命题
and come to find out that insane proposition
恰好完全改变了航天经济的数量级
just so happens to completely shift the economics of spaceflight by orders of magnitude.
我的意思是 我们不再去月球的首要原因是
I mean, the reason we stopped going to the moon in the first place was
因为它是如此昂贵
because it was so expensive
而美国已经(通过阿波罗计划)和苏联的较量 清楚地掂量了自个儿**的份量
and the United States had clearly measured their genitalia against the Soviet Union,
而那并不是探测月球的可持续方式
and that just simply wasn't a sustainable way to explore the moon.
所以 谈及探测月球可持续方式
So, speaking of sustainable ways to explore the moon,
这就是下一部视频我们真正要深入讨论的是 但意外的是其中大部分已经完成了
that's what we'll really dive into in my next video that by happenstance is mostly done already,
所以稍事等待 我们会回答
so standby and we'll answer,
NASA是否应取消SLS然后使用Starship等商业火箭公司
should NASA just cancel SLS and use Starship and other commercial launchers.
因此 在这结束的时候 在我看来
So at the end of the day, in my opinion,
橙色火箭现在够用
orange rocket good enough for now,
闪亮火箭(近未来)前途无量
shiny rocket incredible for the very near future.
而希望合作探索太空的我们 可以庆幸生活在这样一个时代
And we as team space can celebrate the fact that we even live at a time
两种超大型火箭几乎同时上线的时代
where we'll get to have two super mega rockets go online at roughly the same time.
好极了
Yes.
所以 你是怎么想的 你学到啥新东西没？
So what do you think, did you learn anything new?
你改变了你的想法吗？
Did any of your perspectives change?
我知道我的想法变了
I know mine did.
老实说 当我开始做这个视频和脚本的时候
Honestly, when I started making this video and working on the script,
我认为这是一个定局
I thought it was a foregone conclusion.
我以为我什么都知道
I thought that I knew everything,
然后才渐渐发现实际上我应当谦虚地了解
and come to find out it was actually pretty humbling to really go through
所有这些东西是如何运作的且应该自己核实情况
how all this stuff works and just kinda do a reality check for myself.
所以如果你学到了什么
So let me know if you learned anything,
或者改变了什么想法 请务必让我知道
or something shifted in your mind.
我敢肯定的下面的评论已经充满了SLS和Starship的对比
And I'm sure the comments are already still full of SLS versus Starship,
其实也差不多是这个视频的内容
which is kinda what this video's about.
但是我猜我可能真的没有帮助减少Twitter上的争吵
And I'm probably guessing that I really didn't help to reduce the number of Twitter arguments.
对不起 Joe Barnard
Sorry, Joe Barnard.
I have a quick list of people I need to thank for helping with this video.
First off, Boca Chica Mary and NasaSpaceFlight
for providing some of these wonderful images of Starship development.
I'm sure you're already following them,
but in case you haven't, get your butt over there and follow their work.
Then I need to thank Kimi Talvitie, Caspar Stanley,
and Martian Days, who all have helped provide some of the beautiful renders you've seen.
So definitely shoot them a follow.
But also a thanks to Declan Murphy from flightclub.io
for helping me come up with some of these numbers and crunching some stuff.
He started working on a yeet calculator,
which is just awesome.
Thanks to some of the stuff we were working on,
trying to figure out which rockets could do what things.
So definitely check out flightclub.io and check out his Patreon page
if you wanna help him do the awesome work he's doing.
Speaking of Patreon,
I definitely owe a huge thank you to my patron supporters
who've already heard this video so many times before it comes out.
They fact check and do a lot of work for me on the backend,
and it's just awesome.
We have such an incredible community,
so thank you guys for all your help.
If you wanna help add your voice, your opinion,
do some fact checking or just hang out with like-minded space people,
definitely consider becoming a Patreon supporter,
where you'll gain access to our exclusive Subreddit,
our exclusive Discord channel,
and exclusive monthly live streams.
That's patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
Thank you.
And while you're online, be sure and check out my web store,
because we have really cool merchandise like Lunar Mission shirts, which, by the way,
you didn't even get to see the back yet.
Check this out.
Now there's actually a little Easter egg here to this T-shirt.
So notice it says Lunar Mission in this photograph,
but there's actually more to this photograph.
So if you can figure it out,
if you can figure out what else is there besides Lunar Mission,
not the remove shoes before entering cabin,
but the additional words to Lunar Mission.
If you can figure out what the rest of that says,
go ahead and type that in at checkout for a coupon code,
and you'll get 10% off this T-shirt, so good luck.
We have really cool merchandise,
they're all hand-printed here in the United States,
hand sewn on patches.
We're constantly making new stuff.
Get ready, there's going to be a lot of really cool new things.
So check back often,
because some of this stuff is so cool that even Elon Musk wears it, seriously.
That's everydayastronaut.com/shop.
Thanks, everybody, that's gonna do it for me.
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人
[令人振奋的音乐]
[upbeat music]